Register of the William Henry Irwin Papers, 1890-1942.
Hoover Institution Archives
William Henry Irwin Papers,
1890-1942.
48011
Irwin, Will, 1873-1948.
6 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (5.2 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to Herbert Hoover, and to political and social conditions in the U.S. Includes drafts of fictional and other writings by W. H. Irwin, and correspondence with Herbert Hoover.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1948.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Journalism--United States.; United States--Politics and government.; Journalists.
Biographical Note.
1873, Sept. 14 Born, Oneida, New York
1899 A.B., Stanford University
1940 Dr. Humane Letters, Knox College
1896 Editor-in-chief, Daily Palo Alto
1900 Editor, San Francisco Wave
1902-1904 Sunday editor, San Francisco Chronicle
1906-1907 Editor, McClure's Magazine
1914-1915 War correspondent, London Daily Mail
1914-1915 Member of executive committee, Commission for Relief in Belgium
1916-1918 War correspondent, Saturday Evening Post
1918 Chief Foreign Department, Committee on Public Information
1914 Author, BEATING BACK (With Al Jennings)
1925 Author, YOUTH RIDES WEST
1927 Author, HOW RED IS AMERICA?
1927 Author, HIGHLIGHTS OF MANHATTAN
1929 Author, HERBERT HOOVER --A REMINISCENT BIOGRAPHY
1936 Author, PROPAGANDA AND THE NEWS
1940 Author, SPY AND COUNTERSPY (With E. V. Voska)
1942 Author, THE MAKING OF A REPORTER
Series Description
- Letters Received, 1927-1940. (Box No. 1.)
  Letters recieved from Herbert Hoover, arranged chronologically.
- Manuscripts and Related Material, 1890-1942. (Box No. 1-6.)
  Typed and holograph manuscripts of published and unpublished titles by Will Irwin, arranged in two groups (articles/essays and books/serializatons) and thereunder chronologically. Related material, such as correspondence and source data, follows the pertinent manuscript.
- Miscellaneous, 1916-1926. (Box No. 6.)
  Two folders of clippings and memorabilia.
- Printed Matter, 1896-1900. (On shelf following collection.)
  Two bound volumes of newspapers, portions of which apparently are marked for Irwin authorship.
Container List
- LETTERS RECEIVED, 1927-1940
  - Twenty-eight and a half letters received from Herbert Hoover, 1927-1940 (Box 1.)
- MANUSCRIPTS AND RELATED MATERIAL, 1890-1942
  - Articles and essays (Box 1.)
    - High school essays, ca. 1890
    - My Religion
    - The Passing of the Hick
    - How to Talk to Politicians
    - Stop Tinkering with the Movies
    - County Jail - Alias School for Crime
    - Five Coast Guard Articles - synopsis
    - The Royal Giver
    - Kingfish over the White House
    - The Rise of the C.I.O.
    - If Washington had Said "Yes"
    - Crime-crazy
    - Exit the Bank Robber
    - Men See without Eyes
    - Landon of Kansas
    - All Primed for Prohibition
    - Dubinsky Goes on Strike
    - Ten Years of Movie Control
    - Our Adolescent Joiners
    - A Set-back for C.I.O.
    - Catching Up with China
    - We Are Advertised by Our Loving Friends
    - Can They Stand the Gaff
    - Child Health Article
    - Savage America
    - Savage America - (2nd article, "They Lynched the Wrong Man")
    - Is Edgar Hoover on the Spot?
    - Will You Loose Your Birthday?
    - Lewis for President?
    - A Hundred Billions for Pensions?
    - Interview with Herbert Hoover
    - Where Character Education Shows Results
    - Let's Not Be Suckers Again
    - Letters received, January 11, 1940, Brandt Publishers to Will Irwin concerning manuscripts of published articles
  - Books and serializations
    - Beating Back, 1914. With Al J. Jennings
    - Source material for Beating Back (Box 2.)
    - Colonel Charles R. Forbes, 1924
    - Youth Rides West, 1925
    - How Red Is America, 1927
    - Highlights of Manhattan, 1927
      - Holograph draft, incomplete; typed draft, incomplete
    - Herbert Hoover - A Reminiscent Biography, 1929 (Box 3.)
      - First working draft
      - First draft, before Hoover revision, chapters 1-11
      - First draft, before Hoover revision, chapters 12-23 (Box 4.)
      - First draft rewritten, chapters 6-11
      - Final draft, chapters 8-22
      - Final draft rewritten, chapters 9-21
      - Two telegrams concerning manuscript
      - Honors and degrees of Herbert Hoover
      - Published and unpublished reports on U.S. Department of Commerce studies, 1928-1932
      - Letter from Will Irwin to Ruth E. Gosnell, Sept. 2, 1933
    - Propaganda and the News, 1936 (Box 5.)
      - Chapters 1-24, complete
      - Chapters 20-24, copy
    - Spy and Counterspy, 1940. With E. V. Voska
      - Complete Draft
      - Correction and inserts
      - Statement about Dr. Albert's portfolio
    - Making of a Reporter, 1942
      - Synopsis, chapters III to 1933
      - Chapters 1-8
      - Chapters 9-30 (Box 6.)
- MISCELLANEOUS, 1916-1926
  - Clippings, 1916-1926 (Box 6.)
  - Memorabilia
- PRINTED MATTER, 1896-1900
  - "Daily Palo Alto" (Stanford, California), Vols. 8-12 (1896-1900) in one bound volume. Marked portions between September 4, 1896 and December 16, 1896 indicate Irwin authorship (Box On shelf.)
  - "The Wave" (San Francisco, California), Vols. 20-21 (1899-1900) in one bound volume. Marked portions indicate Irwin authorship.